Okay. Uh hello everyone. Can you hear me
in the back?
All good. Okay.
So, uh well, welcome back everyone.
Am I uh echoing? All good. Okay. So, um,
today I'd like to talk about context
management for long context agents. And
I at first thought about titling this as
like context management for long context
LLMs because most of the stuff I'm going
to be talking about today is kind of
more general LLM stuff, but long context
is super super important for when we're
working on agents and it's not
necessarily covered uh, very well in all
of the LLM prerequisite classes. So, I'm
going to cover it in a fair amount of
detail today. I'm also going to try to
go through kind of the long context
architectures that are used in many of
the kind of state-of-the-art open uh
models so you can kind of see the best
practices that everybody is using in
order to handle a very long context.
So first I'd like to talk a little bit
about um how long an agent context can
grow.
So basically the input is quadratic uh
from the uh or the number of token
accesses that you do is quadratic uh
based on the linear history growth. So
um if each call uh you make for an agent
takes about you know five tokens and
let's say you start out with a an
initial system prompt of one token uh
you'll get six tokens in the first call
11 16 uh 21 and 26. you know, this will
increase and increase and increase. Um,
and so by the time you have gotten to
the end, you will, if you do things
completely naively, you will have had to
process ADK tokens uh for these five
calls. And you know, this can continue
for a very long time. I I don't know the
longest anybody has used a single coding
agent session or something like that,
but I've certainly done them for like
multiple days uh where I've been working
with it for almost the entire day. So
you could imagine this could get uh very
very large. Um the actual computational
complexity of this is uh is actually
even larger than this. Um
well no sorry. So yeah the the
computational complexity is is quadratic
here.
So why do agent prompts get so long uh
so quickly? I did a little bit of data
analysis on uh the composition of
prompts that I used in um uh 1,500
sessions from our uh coding agent
openhands. And
each each session was relatively short.
These are not like the long multi-day
sessions that you do. This is more like
solving a single task. But uh each one
used about 78,000 tokens on average. Um
23% of this was a system prompt in all
of the tool descriptions. Uh this is
relatively large for a coding agent. I
think our system prompt is somewhere on
the order of like 15,000 to 18,000
tokens because we're very opinionated.
Uh the open ants agent is very
opinionated about how people uh do work.
Um these tend to vary from like 8,000 to
uh 8,000 to 20,000 tokens depending on
you know how many tools you uh you pull
in and stuff like this. Um separately
from this uh 9% were user messages. So
this is the user either saying the
initial task or following up with uh
additional information after that. 9%
were reasoning traces um and you know
where the model is thinking through
things. 2% were model replies. Sorry,
this isn't showing on the slide, but 2%
were um the model replying directly to
the user. So, it's spending about um
five times as many tokens freezing as it
is spending communicating uh with text
to the user. And 20% were tool calls. Uh
so, you know, uh you know, writing code,
uh reading code, that sort of thing. And
37% were tool results. So, this is uh
you know, getting the result of, you
know, reading a file or something like
this.
So you know each step can uh will
consist of all of these and that tends
to add up uh very quickly.
So when you're handling this very long
context uh there's two big challenges
here. Uh the first one is capacity and
so whether your model is able to handle
this large amount of uh evidence in the
first place and this is a challenge uh
because as I'll talk about in a little
bit training models to handle very long
context is hard
um and so in order to manage this you
need uh things like architecture
position encoding training data uh and
uh you also need to be able to evaluate
whether you're doing a good job of this.
And then the second thing is efficiency
uh and whether the system can afford to
serve it. And there's a bunch of
techniques to do that as well. And I I
think some people might be taking this
for granted if you're just using, you
know, cloud code or codeex or something
like this, but they're doing some pretty
monumental feats of engineering to take
a, you know, multi- trillion parameter
model and serve it within seconds uh to
uh over and over and over again for mil
I don't know codeex has 25 million
users. So you can imagine uh 25 million
daily users hitting it every few seconds
for this huge model. Uh if you want to
you can calculate in your head how many
flops per uh per second that might be.
It's a lot of flops.
Cool. Um so any questions or things?
Probably pretty straightforward I guess.
Okay. So uh let's go into inference. And
so in order to make this happen uh the
you basically need to be able to um
calculate uh prefill and decoding. So uh
calculate your inputs and your outputs
at each step. And this uh you know I'm
sure everybody has done in your previous
classes uh for generating from uh you
know a language model. some things you
may or may not have thought about in
your previous classes. If you took how
many people took like uh language model
systems or deep learning systems or
something like that actually more than I
thought. So if you took the systems
course you you probably handled this. Um
but other things you need to think about
are how do you schedule uh multiple
concurrent queries? Um and also how do
you save the results in the KV cache uh
so you can reuse them and not have to
reuse them over and over again. uh not
have to calculate over and over again.
So going into a bit more detail here, um
we have a few phrase uh phases in
inference. The first one is called
prefill. Um you could also call it
encoding. Um but I think pre prefill is
kind of the like preferred term of art
nowadays. And so you take in all of your
input tokens uh that you don't need to
generate and uh you generate the key and
value pairs uh from each of them. And
then uh when you're decoding you
basically uh take the prompt uh and key
value pairs um generate an output and
append uh the key value pair that you
get from the output. So um you do this
kind of incrementally whereas this can
be done in a batched sequence.
And so uh when we think about this as a
serving system, there's a bunch of ways
we quantify how good a serving system
is. Uh the first one is time to first
token. So this is how long you need to
start um you need to wait between when
you start uh
entering a query and when you start
seeing the first output. And so like I'm
sure everybody you know who uses chat
GPT or something like that uh you put in
a long output you notice it takes longer
to start getting a response than if you
put in sorry put in a long input you see
it takes longer to start getting a
response than if you put in a short
input and that's like your TTFT is
higher. Uh then uh your time per output
token is the uh time like the amount of
time it takes uh between generating each
token. And if you go to a website like
open router
um
t typically uh here this will be your
time per output token there I am pretty
sure they're not counting prefill here
and it's just like the time between uh
each of the tokens that might be a
little bit small with the black
background but you can see that um for
GLM 5.2 to uh you have like 63, 48, uh
24, uh that sort of thing. And you know,
some providers are drastically better
than others. Like this provider,
not to pick on Mistl, but they're
getting, you know, three three tokens
per second and then these other ones
like Parasel and Coreweave are getting,
you know, hundreds of tokens per second.
So um so basically uh you know this
makes a huge difference in your
experience using um uh using agents. Uh
one other interesting thing is um
there's different ways people can use
agents. And so in some cases you might
really hear about this. So like let's
say you're working together um with a an
agent on a interactive task in your
favorite coding CLI. you may really
really care about, you know, TTFT and
Tapot. Um, if you're running an agent in
the background to do some background
tasks that run overnight, you might not
care at all. Um, and there's trade-offs
between them, between like throughput
and cost and how fast uh you can get the
the tokens. And like I you know also um
serve coding agents uh with my company
and when I talk to providers they'll
often often ask which do you care about
more so we can optimize the system uh
for the one you care about more and so
um there's uh there's ways you can do
that and I'll I'll talk about those too.
Cool.
Um yeah so sorry just to finish the
slide. So throughput is um the completed
tokens or requests divided by the wall
clock time. So this is kind of seen
usually on a more holistic level over
the whole system. And then uh the cost
is you know how much it costs.
So as a refresher um I I hopefully
everybody should know this already. Um
but you have uh the
uh query key and value calculation in uh
typical attention and this is uh so you
have this here and then you take the
softmax um divide it by this. You might
have some sort of uh you know positional
uh bias and then you calculate your
output and typical full attention uh
looks uh like this. you mask all the
previous tokens and and or you consider
all the current tokens and you mask all
the um the future tokens.
Um so this is of course very expensive
because it's quadratic in the sequence
length. Uh and so a lot of the stuff I'm
going to be talking about today is about
how to fix that.
Um so this is on the efficiency side and
then on the effectiveness side just
because you have a model or just because
you have a serving system that can take
in you know a million tokens doesn't
necessarily mean that you can use that a
million tokens effectively and
um this is a very like old school
example of this I guess this is a needle
in the haststack evaluation how many
people have seen this figure for
maybe some but not not that many. Okay,
so to explain what this looks like,
basically what this is saying is um it's
a very weird evaluation. Basically, they
um they took a whole bunch of Paul
Graham essays uh by the like famous
entrepreneur and head of Y Combinator
Paul Graham and they stuck in uh
something about like the best place in
San Francisco to eat a sandwich is
something or other and then they ask a
question where's the best place in San
Francisco to eat a sandwich and then the
language model has to answer that
correctly. um and they made the context
longer and longer and longer and then
they evaluate uh models with the longer
context and eventually the weaker models
start getting worse at these very very
long contexts and there's a bunch of
examples of things like this. Um ruler
and helmet are kind of the the common
benchmarks that people use here. Um but
basically uh the long the summary is
that if you have very long context your
models might start getting worse at
processing them.
So has anybody noticed this when you've
used a coding agent for a long time like
are there common
or used any agent for a long time are
there common like failure cases that you
see?
What what kind of things what kind of
things have bothered you?
Anybody?
>> Yeah.
>> Forget the previous context.
>> Yeah. Forgets the previous context. Did
that cause any like problems for you?
>> Yeah.
with me telling it not to do something
in the middle of the conversation and
then it goes and does it. Um there there
was a really bad example uh where I
think actually Daniel talked about it
here where the person had said do not
delete this and then it went and deleted
it anyway because it had forgotten the
context. So yeah, this can be a really
big problem in agentic settings because
you know the user is giving these
incremental instructions. So
so I'm going to be talking about several
different things. I'm going to be
talking about architecture. I'm going to
be talking about training inference and
compaction. So going first into
architecture. Um this is both about
efficiency and accuracy.
And so as I mentioned standard attention
is global. So it makes pairwise
comparisons across uh all of the tokens
here. And um the problem with this is uh
like this is quadratic obviously. And
does anyone know the like standard
length of the of models nowadays of
these uh of like state-of-the-art
language models?
>> 256 to a million.
>> 256 to a million. Yeah. And I I'd say
most people are aiming for a million now
because they don't want to be the, you
know, the model that has 256 when
everyone else has a million. So very
quick math in your head, how many
pairwise comparisons is that?
>> 10 12
>> 10 10^ the 12 or in English.
>> A trillion. Yeah, that's a trillion.
That's a trillion comparisons every
time. uh like when you're uh generating
a sequence of a million long and each
comparison uh requires you to multiply
large vectors by each other over and
over and over again. So you're starting
to get up into the you know 10 to the
I guess it'd probably be 10 to the 20ish
uh which is a lot that that's a lot of
compute um for a single sequence.
So um there there's ways that people
solve this and basically almost all of
them fall into the category of taking
this quadratic computation and putting
some sort of constant limit on the
number of comparisons that are made uh
at each time step. And that brings your
uh n squared down to owl where I I wrote
w for window but it doesn't necessarily
need to be a window. It just needs to be
the cap on the number of comparisons
that you're making.
Um so there's the idea of local models
and global models. And so local models
are are basically models where this cap
on computation happens within a local
window. And then global models you have
a cap on you might or might not have a
cap on computation but that cap on
computation is not localized. So you can
pass information uh throughout the
entire sequence. And the I'd say almost
all of the models uh that exist nowadays
or are widely popular nowadays are some
variety of hybrid model where they have
many local computations and then one
global computation then many local
computations one global computation
and specifically I'm going to talk about
six uh models that we have here. So uh
the most recent Quen model uh has uh
local computation of uh gated delta net.
I'll explain all of these uh or most of
these in a bit. And then um sparse
retrieval uh for the global computation
and the ratio is 3:1.
Uh GLM 5.3 is uh also a variety of delta
um and sparse attention uh with 3:1.
Um
uh Kim K3 is uh a variety of Delta and
um this is a dense uh dense attention
3:1.
Uh Neimotron is Mamba uh which is uh
kind of like recurrent style model
and uh dense attention 4:1.
um to uh window uh sliding window
attention uh dense attention 5 to one
and deepseek's a little bit different.
It kind of has uh window windowed
attention but then some uh sparsity uh
sparse stuff with interle branches. So
um basically the the standard way of
doing things is hybrid model uh with
some sort of local thing and uh either
sparse or dense uh global attention.
So I'm I'm going to be talking about
this. I'm not going to go into like a
ton of details for all of them, but uh
it should be enough that you could be
able to look them up later.
So the first one is uh sliding window
attention. And this is maybe the the
simplest conceptually. And what you do
is you take chunks or uh you take chunks
of the output and basically you're able
to attend to your current chunk and um
all of the previous chunks and uh
or not all of the previous chunks, a
fixed number of previous chunks. So if
this is your current chunk, um it might
be a chunk of like 512 tokens or
something like this. You would have an
additional 512 and 512 tokens in the
previous chunks and you would attend to
those. Um so pretty simple, no changes
to attention, but you have something
like this. But the nice thing about this
is on the first layer you're passing
information from the previous one or two
chunks, but on the next layer the uh
previous chunks also have information
from their previous chunks. And so you
kind of get this gradually expanding
window. Um
so uh this uh this is pretty widely
used.
Um but the more popular way of doing
things nowadays is using some variety of
linear attention.
And so the way uh linear attention works
is basically we take our uh standard
attention and standard attention has
this um softmax operation included in
it. And this is the reason why it's hard
to compute because you're taking the
exponent and um and dividing. And
because you do this there's you
basically have no choice but to expand
all of the uh key and query computations
uh like key query multiplication
computations in and be uh quadratic uh
quadratic
complexity.
What linear attention does is you
basically start from this uh kind of
standard attention formulation but you
take you remove the softmax and the
normalization here or I mean the
normalization doesn't really matter but
you remove the softmax and you get just
the key query multiplication
and [clears throat]
this is definitely less expressive
because basically what you're doing is
you're moving
from something that
takes in a bunch of uh like numbers.
Anyway, like pretend pretend that this
bottom one adds up to one, but you're
going from a thing that takes a bunch of
real numbers and normalizes them into
probability like numbers that are
between zero and one and add to one. Um,
so this nonlinearity allows you to focus
on like only some of the previous uh
like tokens. And this is kind of the
good point of attention. That's the
selling point of attention that allows
you to focus on the relevant previous
context. And you're basically taking
away that ability, right? You're you're
removing the relative comparisons and
just getting um the the dotproduct
between the queries and keys. But it
allows you to do something really uh
nice which is that you can use uh the
associative
uh you can use associivity and basically
rearrange
so that um you can convert the sum of
all the key and value uh multiplications
before into a single uh state matrix.
And so this state matrix is essentially
a function that map it's a linear
function that maps from a query to a
value. So attention is also a linear
value. So if I go back to this here
you're basically calculating you're
taking the query you're calculating the
attention over all the keys you're
multiplying it by the values and you're
getting a value here. Um and this state
matrix is also that. But the nice part
about it is this state matrix can be
decomposed. So you can update it. You
can keep this state matrix around and
update it in constant time every time
you get a new value. So this essentially
becomes like a recurrent neural network.
So it it allows you to update the state
matrix um in linear time without having
uh without requiring the quadratic
computation.
So
this basically solves your quadratic
problem and it solves it so much
that um O of N squ becomes O of N.
There's no like there's no even W term
in this because uh each time you're uh
you're updating based entirely on the
previous state. Um but there's there's
caveats here. So um is this clear though
uh so far?
Okay, cool.
Um, so the big caveat is exactly the
caveat I mentioned before. Like this is
just a less expressive function. Um, and
it doesn't allow you to make like
relative comparisons between the
previous tokens, that sort of thing. So
there's a bunch of uh workarounds around
this to try to make a more expressive
function that nonetheless is useful in
um in kind of uh doing attention-like
calculations. And so um most of these
are
if you dig deep into the math in them,
they're basically trying to become
better predictors of the final value
that you would get from attention. Um
and you you can dig into the papers to
see how that works, but I'm going to
explain them mostly uh mechanistically
here. And so um the first thing is
Delta. And the idea behind deltaNet is
um you can predict what
um
you can essentially predict what value
you would want to be getting from the uh
from the calculation of uh KT
um and S. And so you know KT here is uh
the key at time step t and you are
comparing it with the matrix at time
step t uh t minus one and uh you're
calculating this v hat t and
on the other hand you um so basically
this this is the prediction that you
would get of kt But on the other hand,
you know what the uh output VT should be
uh based on um what the query times uh
or based on uh what the
Hang on one second. [laughter]
I don't want to I don't want to get this
wrong. So
you calculate KT with respect to the
matrix. And you can view this matrix as
a way of uh calculating the uh the way
of calculating the mapping from a query
to a value. And you can also get the the
actual value and subtract out uh what
the value you get when multiplying it
from the previous uh together with the
previous matrix is. And this is
essentially the error uh that you get
here. And then you want to reduce the
error. And so in order to reduce this
error, what you do is you um essentially
add in this uh this term which is KT uh
times the error term. And after you do
this, if you multiply in KT to the new
matrix, you will no longer have any
error. But you don't want to make an
update that is too big. So you add this
beta term. This is essentially a
learning, it's similar to a learning
rate. And this learning rate will make
the updates uh smaller. And so uh if you
if you do this, this allows you to
basically nudge the matrix in the
direction of uh the in the direction
that will cause a query that looks like
the current key to output the value that
you want essentially. So it's it's
reducing the error uh reducing the error
in the prediction of the value that you
want.
So um as I said this is going to be a
little bit high level. Um the the papers
are are pretty good uh descriptions of
this.
Um so after this um this basically what
this is doing is this is pushing you in
the direction of the uh of making the
the matrix a better predictor of the uh
the value. But one problem with this is
you can build up lots and lots of
context uh from the previous uh spots
and linear attention doesn't have any
mechanism to prevent very far away cont
uh context from having a bad
influence on your next predictions. And
so if you have like a very weird key far
back in the future, it might have a very
big influence on you in the f uh in the
future. And so the way they fix this is
basically they have a decay term to make
uh to make the
matrix decay
a little bit at every time step. And by
decaying the matrix a little bit at
every time step, they're basically
discounting the the far in the past
context. And so you multiply um the
matrix by alpha t and then you add this
uh st tilda into uh into your
calculation here and update the matrix.
And so the stronger you make this decay
basically the the more quickly uh it
will forget the previous context. And so
you can make this more local or or less
local.
And so this is uh gated delta is used in
the Quen models. So it's one of the more
uh the more popular methods now. Um but
both uh GLM and uh KI which are kind of
two of the state-of-the-art models use a
slightly more expressive version of this
uh where they basically have a per
element uh decay term. So each element
can decay at a different speed. And uh
because each element decays at a
different speed, you can have some uh
portions of the context that uh you know
carry over very long time periods, some
portions of the context that carry over
very short time periods.
Cool. So hopefully this was more or less
uh more or less legible. Um
any any questions here?
Long long story short, it's basically a
way to turn uh into
um it's a way to turn
the idea of attention to something that
you can calculate um in context. Mamba
is uh something that's very similar um
but it's a little bit more
mathematically involved um uh and I I
decided to skip over it. uh I covered it
more in the uh language model uh
description course but similar idea but
just a bit more complex uh in the math.
So the next thing I'd like to talk about
is sparse attention. And so sparse
attention is uh basically looking up a
not attending to everything in the
previous context but only attending to
some things in the previous context. And
essentially you limit the number of
things that you look up in the previous
context. There's a few ways you can do
it. Um originally in there was a sparse
attention paper by OpenAI uh quite a
while ago like 5 years ago or something
like this. Um and basically uh what they
did was they had sparse attention every
you know uh 512 tokens or something like
this. And what this does is it means
that you still have a fixed it's still
quadratic in the sequence length but
it's 512 times less than if you attended
to every token and that's like good
enough uh that you can manage to
calculate it over the context that
you're interested in.
Another option is to do um content
dependent sparse attention. And
basically what this does is you have a
very cheap way of calculating attention.
Like for example, you can down project
the attention vectors to be very very
small and then you do attention over
these very very small uh attention
vectors. You pick the top k ones and
then you do full attention over the top
k. So uh that's uh another way that you
can do this
and this is what's used in deepseek.
Yeah.
>> How do we define the metric for which we
do the top similarity compared in this
in the shrine space we just do like
coine distance.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I I think it's typically not
cosine but it's just product but yeah
>> I I I think although maybe maybe they're
normalizing beforehand. They actually
don't know that detail.
Any other questions?
So basically um these
th this is a very very cheap way to
achieve global attention because you can
just uh write a kernel that will do this
for you. Um this over here will uh
require you to have two passes, but you
know it's potentially uh more accurate.
So um I I've seen both of these used
pretty widely.
So a final um a final thing is KV
compression. How many people saw this in
a language modeling course?
Maybe some people. Okay. Um so I will uh
I'll explain this. So basically um this
is standard multi head attention. And so
in standard multi-head attention, you
have a bunch of heads and each one has
values and keys and all of these are a
certain dimension. So they're like
dimension, let's say they're dimension D
and you have uh you have like a certain
number of heads. Let's say that's H. Um
so
the two main ways that people solve uh
or help uh this problem of having very
uh large and expensive KV caches is uh
grouped query attention. And grouped
query attention basically uh just uses a
smaller number than h um you usually h
divided by some uh power of two uh
number of uh keys and values. And
because it's the KV cache, it's not the
KVQ cache. Um
if you reduce the number of uh keys and
values that are used, you reduce the
amount of memory that you need to hold
the KV cache. This is really important
because if it gets very large then um it
limits the number you can fit on one GPU
and so this can usually be reduced by
like four or by eight or something like
that. Um multiquery attention is just
like grouped query attention with a
single one. So you can kind of almost
skip over that. You already know what it
means. Um multi head latent attention
the the um
is essentially down projecting uh the
size of the keys and values. So it's not
reducing the number of heads, it's
making each head smaller. And so this is
similar to what I talked about with the
top K attention. Um and of course you
can combine both of these together as
well. You could have group query
attention with um you know smaller uh
keys of values.
Uh any any questions here?
Okay, cool.
Um so the these are the method the
architectural methods that people use to
handle very long contexts and with these
um you can handle up to a million uh
tokens. So like this is uh you know this
makes the efficiency possible.
The next thing is uh training long
context models. And this is actually uh
pretty hard. And the reason why is
because um if we want something to
handle 128k tokens or even more, there's
actually not that much data on the
internet that is 128k coherent tokens.
Um it's actually a lot of a lot of data.
it's more than most Wikipedia articles,
you know, um you're starting to get in
the in the order of like having a book
uh that you need to have and there's not
that many books on the internet. So,
typically what you do is you start out
with like short pre-training. Um you do
more continued training with longer
documents and then you do long
adaptation.
Um I wrote packed sequences here. Um,
but packed sequences are are useful can
be useful for efficiency, but they're
not super useful for learning long
contexts because um every time you like
let's say you pack 10 documents into a
sequence, you're not learning to attend
across the documents and in fact you
probably should not be. So um you really
need coherent uh long sets of data to do
adaptation to very long contexts.
Um so I'm going to talk about a few
things that we do here. Um the first
thing I'm going to talk about is uh
handling positional encodings. Um so
absolute positional encodings uh I I
hope everybody has seen in their
language modeling class. Um but
basically uh each individual
entry in the uh
each individual word embedding uh gets a
position vector and that position vector
is typically calculated by uh some sort
of function like using signs and
cosiness and other stuff like this. So
hopefully you know most people have seen
this. So I'll I'll kind of skip over
that. Also maybe most people have seen
rope. Are people generally familiar with
rope? Okay, I see a fair number of
people. I see actually less people uh
than I would have expected, but um uh
maybe people are just uh not interested
in raising your hand. Um [laughter] but
uh but basically um rope rope is pretty
elegant mathematically in my opinion. Uh
basically the problem they were trying
to solve is they wanted to have a
positional embedding. um where the
positional uh or positional encoding
where the positional encoding is
entirely
determined by the relative distance uh
between two tokens.
And the
reason why they wanted to do this is
they didn't they didn't want the
absolute position to have an effect on
uh they didn't want the absolute
position to have an effect on whether
two tokens would attend to each other.
And so
this is this has been quite effective
and a lot of uh a lot of models use
rope. Um the the math I'm not going to
go through here because it's kind of not
the main point, but they do some
interesting stuff with rotations and
imaginary numbers and stuff like this.
Um but there's also this like super
counterintuitive
uh nope.
which is uh don't don't use positional
encodings at all. Um and if you took
your uh class on transformers
uh you might have heard this scary stuff
which is like you need positional
encodings for transformers because
otherwise something in position one in
position five will have exactly the same
representation. So if you have like this
this is a cat but this is not a cat it
will attend to both of the cats the same
amount or something like this. Um
theoretically when the transformers were
originally created um this might have
been true but now actually it's it's not
true anymore based on the transformers
we use now. Um anybody have an idea
why this is the case? I've kind of given
a hint in the slide but
you might also need to know a little bit
of the history of transformers uh which
is uh before we were using encoder
decoder models uh where the encoders
encoded all of the input and then the
decoders uh generated the output any
idea
>> because we're doing causal masking
exactly so um to elaborate on that a
little bit if I go back to our
transformer equation
Um, we have the keys um, and the
queries. And if we look at the queries,
even if you have cat at position two and
cat at position five, the cat at
position two is only attending to the
previous token where the cat at position
five is attending to the previous four
tokens. Um, and so both of them are like
actually different. um starting at least
in the first layer of attention. And so
you can tell like even if they are
exactly the same word, the embeddings
starting in the first layer of attention
will will not be different. And there's
kind of uh this counterintuitive paper
that demonstrates that you don't need uh
positional encodings at all. And this is
especially true um this is in auto
reggressive uh transformers. In non-auto
reggressive transformers where you're
attending all the tokens are attending
to each other. You still do need
positional encodings. Um
this is especially true when we start
talking about like gated delta because
gated delta has like the decay term and
uh other things like this which causes
each uh token to be different. So once
we start having those sort of local
biases, we actually don't need
positional uh encodings anymore.
Um
and
if you uh if you look um
we uh the first two here have rope uh or
at least partial rope. The second two
have nope uh no positional attend
encodings. Um the the fourth one uh
relies entirely on implicit order and
mamba and some of them in uh and inkling
has relative positional encodings. So
you can see that it's kind of like half
split between having relative positional
encodings and not at all. But like let's
say we did have positional encodings. Uh
one thing you need to worry about for
long context is uh position
interpolation or position extension. And
what this means is if you have a
pre-training range, um, you need to
essentially extend your model so that
it's able to handle longer sequences.
And so the the promise of rope was that
rope relied only on the relative
position uh between the different tokens
in the output. But
that that's fine as long as the relative
position is only um well okay there
there's two reasons why this is not
fine. So number one if you're training
on
sequences of length L and then you
extend to sequences uh of length SL then
it's never seen two tokens attend to
each other over a distance of more than
L. So the tokens that are more than L
away from each other are going to have
problems attending to each other and
you're not going to be able to uh manage
that very well. Um the other problem is
that actually relative positional
encodings are only one part of the story
and like actually the auto reggressive
mask has an effect in all these other
things. So you can't just take rope and
expect it to work uh really well on
longer sequences.
And so the typical way you fix this is
there's a parameter in rope that
basically
uh
let me see if I have it in my slide.
So I I don't I don't really have it in
my slide, but there's basically a um a
parameter in rope theta that uh tells
you how much you rotate at each time
step. and you divide this theta by the
uh multiplier by which you extended the
sequence. And so basically you're
stretching the rope position so that the
rope uh position at position zero would
um or the rope position at position like
five would be 5s uh would be equivalent
to the position 5s in your uh extended
context.
And there's also um a more sophisticated
way of doing this called yarn uh which
basically is uh similar
in spirit uh to like the delta uh the ki
delta attention
um which
basically said that we want some of them
to be very long distance and some of
them to not be very long distance. In
yarn essentially you have some of them
be uh extended more and some of them be
extended less and so you don't um you
don't necessarily interpolate all of
them at the same frequency.
So um yeah in the interest of time I'm
not going to go into like a lot of
detail about this but basically these
are um uh these are the various methods
that you can use here.
So, um,
I'd like to talk a little bit now, um,
taking a step back from the detailed
modeling stuff and going into the data
that you can use to train this. So, um,
as I mentioned before, packed examples,
you can just pack a whole bunch of stuff
in there, um, a whole bunch of documents
in into your context length. And this
will work at training models to be able
to process things near the end of your
context window. But what it won't work
for is the kind of global coherence. And
um so there's a number of different ways
that people do this. One way is just to
find um very long documents uh like
books or something like this. There
aren't a lot of these uh but there are
books. There are code bases and code
bases tend to be coherent. So you can
just download a big codebase and that
will definitely have more tokens. Um
multi-document corpora of some kind. So,
you know, like uh you can get a whole
bunch of documents that are on the same
topic and then at least you'll have
topical coherence between them. Um I've
also seen people train on patents
because patents have like there's lots
of public data for them and you can kind
of link link them together.
A big source nowadays is agent
trajectories because you know agents can
make very very long trajectories if you
just interact with them for a little
while. So that's another one. And then
you can also create synthetic tasks and
a lot of the evaluations are synthetic
tasks. So you can do that as well.
Um and I I have some examples of how the
models do this. Um a lot of the model
training companies don't like to share
these details with you because this is
like if they release their um well so
number one the closed models like
anthropic open AAI you know those places
uh uh Gemini they will not release even
their architectural details the open
model companies have to release their
architectural details otherwise you
can't run their model so what do they
keep secret they keep their data mixes
and their their training strategy secret
so um this there's a lot less detailed
stuff that we can say. Um, but there's
uh all of them explain all of the ones
in here explain a little bit about their
data mixtures and they are things like
uh cleaned up sampled documents and
video um documents, repository files,
issue, PRs, uh long document QA,
scientific papers and technical reports.
And then uh they also create a bunch of
synthetic tasks. And typically they have
a scaling strategy of like 8 64 256 1
million uh that that sort of stuff as
well.
Oh yes. Um [clears throat]
one other
logistical detail that you might need to
deal with um or might not need to deal
with depending on the size of the model
you're training. like for example for
your project if you want to start
dealing with um uh larger models is
context parallelism and basically what
this means is there's a bunch of uh ways
to do parallelism when training models I
wrote context parallelism up here what
are two other ways uh that you can
parallelize models during model training
or serving
>> yes
>> data parallelism
>> yeah you you said a more specific
example of the second one but data
parallelism and I would say model
parallelism in general and model
parallelism can have lots of varieties.
It can have uh expert parallelism where
you have different experts on different
machines uh tensor more generally tensor
parallelism where you split um uh the uh
the parameters and you can also have
pipeline parallelism where you have
different layers on different uh
different devices. But context
parallelism starts becoming import more
important for agents because when you
train agents you want to train them on
very long contexts. And so uh the way
this works is you will compute like one
part of the context uh the keys and
values. So you send it to the next
device calculate the keys and values for
the next for that part send it to the
next device uh and etc etc. So um this
is uh very useful. It's really important
if you start getting above like 32k
32k context or so. Um, but it's also a
pain because
you have the
um
you have all the modeling people saying
I want my I want my KI delta attention
and then you have all the info people
saying but wait I need to implement a
context parallel kernel for KI delta
attention and make sure it actually
works and you can back prop through it
and all of these other things. So um I I
personally had an experience where I was
trying to train uh Quen uh for uh like a
smaller quen model like 135 uh 35b and
uh I I wanted to go do use context
parallelism on it and it's like there's
no kernel for gated delta net anywhere
on the internet and so um you need to uh
you need to either go in and implement
that kernel or decide to do something
else. So um th those two can conflict
some of the times. So be be aware I
guess
um the the good news is for like
standard attention and sliding window
attention and stuff like that all of
those will have uh kernels more easily
implemented. The hard parts are where
you're like not doing a standard
attention operation.
Cool.
Okay. So the next part I'd like to talk
about is prompt and KV caching. This is
uh very important even if you're not the
person who's implementing the language
model, but also if you're just a person
who's um
like running agents uh yourself, but I'm
going to talk about uh the the technical
details of how it's implemented. So, you
know, at least you you have a good uh
idea about how that works. So um
basically
when we I I simplified this a little bit
but when we're generating an agent call
we have an input uh we have an output uh
so this could be like the the messages
and tool calls and then we have the tool
result and so so
as we calculate the input we do prefill
and as we calculate the output uh we do
uh basically decoding Right? And so
during prefill and decoding, we have to
calculate the KV cache. This is all done
in a batch. Uh this is done every time
we generate a token. But after we have
that, we have the uh key and value uh
for each of the positions up until the
end of the output. And so what we can do
is we can throw that in a cache and then
we don't need to calculate it anymore.
The tool result is new uh because you
know we don't calculate over the tool
result. So this becomes a new input and
we generate an output and we get another
tool result. And so in step two we need
to calculate the KV cache over the new
input and we uh during prefill and the
output but we can reuse the cache
and then we do that over and over and
over again. And so as you imagine um as
you can imagine I just showed steps 1 2
3 but by the time we get to step 50 if
we haven't done anything tricky with our
output this is going to be 50 times
larger than the new input in the in the
output right so that's pretty
significant savings if we can cache this
properly
and here are some examples from actual
papers uh that you know examine this and
basically What we can see is this is
like the the token length on uh
different GPUs and this is the amount of
uh of compute that you need with caching
and no caching. And so the upper one of
the same color is uh or the lower one
with the same color is caching and the
the upper one is no caching. So uh
basically as the sequence gets longer
the non-cashed one becomes quadratic and
the cache one is is mostly linear.
This also shows up in how much you pay
to run an agent. And so I I pulled all
of these numbers from uh the official
pricing. And basically you can see here
that if you go through all of these uh
all of these numbers including the
commercial ones typically cashed tokens
are onetenth of the price of uncashed
tokens. And so what this means is you
need to be very aware of uh whether your
tokens are being cached or not. Uh
because if they're not being cached uh
you're going to be paying a lot of money
to be running your agents. Um,
so does anyone have an idea of what a
good uh cash hit rate is
if you're running an agent? Yeah.
>> 80 to 90%.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, yeah. So I I heard 80 to 90% I heard
like more than 95%. I my my impression
is 90 to 95 is everything is fine. Like
I'm I'm good with 90 to 95. If it's less
than that, you might be fine, but you
might be might be losing out somewhere.
Um so, uh yeah, so basically you can you
can cache most of your tokens. Um one
other interesting thing is the output
also tends to be five times more than
the input. So um this is uh there's a
50x difference between output and cached
input which just reflects the amount of
uh uh the amount of cost uh savings that
you can get from serving it.
So why why is caching um so much cheaper
is maybe kind of obvious. You just need
to look up um you need to look up the
outputs. uh you just need to look these
up instead of like actually uh
performing the calculation over them. Uh
especially the feed forward network
calculation is pretty expensive in
transformers and so being able to skip
that is is uh particularly a win. Um but
how do we actually manage that? So
um the first thing is uh how do you hold
it in memory? And there's two like most
popular open-source
uh two most popular open-source
LLM serving libraries VLM and SGLANG and
both of them are based on an innovation
around the how you manage KV caching. Um
so VLM's main technical in innovation
and like of course they have a lot more
stuff in there now. They're like general
purpose serving libraries, but like the
main technical innovation that led to
VLM was something called page detention.
And basically the way it works is you
have physical GPU memory blocks and you
rear you arrange them like kind of
memory blocks or or disk blocks on uh
like more typical uh like CPUbased
machines. And so you might have uh block
zero uh block one block two that you
actually need to calculate and they put
that you know in like block one and then
block seven and then block three or
sorry uh block seven block one block
three and then you have an index to each
one of these uh as you're generating.
And the reason why they wanted to do
this is they want to be able to generate
in parallel many sequences in parallel
and when you finish generating um you
can like evict that from your memory and
so you can uh evict whole blocks at once
and this makes the calculation more more
efficient. So um this is uh one
technical trick that they used to make
this uh you know make parallel serving
work.
Um
the technical innovation that kind of
led to SG lang in particular uh was
something called RAIX attention and this
is specifically focused around uh like
re reusing already cached uh out uh
inputs. And so what they do is they form
a a tree basically uh it's a radics tree
and they use this to look up prefixes
that have been used already. And so this
uh when it first came out this was
specifically focused around uh chat bots
like chatgpt
uh because you know you can have
somebody start a conversation and then
continue the conversation and so you'll
be caching some portion of the already
done conversation. But for uh now it's
like much much more important for agents
because agent conversations are much
longer and much more frequent. So we
need this uh looking up more frequently.
Um so another uh another thing that you
need to think about um which is handled
in uh newer versions of sglang for
instance is let's say you're doing
multi-achine serving. So you're serving
on um you know different machines uh you
know maybe you have a data center with
like 64 nodes or 128 nodes or something
like this. um every time a request comes
in, you want to route it to the machine
that has your KV cache that has the best
KV cache for you um to be accessing and
so that you actually have cache aware
routing uh route it to the appropriate
place and then have the worker with the
best uh KV cache match uh process set.
And so
I love getting all my uh my serving
statistics from Open Router um because
they have so much data and uh they cover
all of the things I want to talk about,
but I believe they even have
a ranking of providers by cash hit rate.
[laughter]
I'm sorry mist the data the data doesn't
lie but um you can see uh mistrol has
the worst cache hit rate and then um you
have other one other ones like Alibaba
cloud or dicard or silicon flow that
have higher cash hit rates um this is
not entirely reflective of the provider
being bad or something like that it
could be just the workloads that they're
running but there's a number of things
that like actually factor into
into this cache hit rate and um one of
them one of them is how good is the cash
routing. The other one is how fast is
the cash eviction. Um so the providers
will not hold your cash for you forever.
Um they will uh you know evict your cash
after a certain amount of time. Does
anyone know how long this is for like
popular providers? Have you ever taken a
look at that
>> yet?
Close to an hour.
>> Close to an hour. I I think the long
like I'm not I'm not like super up to
date on this, but I know anthropic used
to be five minutes. And so it's
basically if you have a an active
conversation going on with them and you
don't pause your conversation, you'll
stay in the cache. Otherwise, if you
like stop the conversation, you get
evicted from the cache. I think you at
least have an option to go up to an hour
now. Um but I don't know if you um but
like it costs a little bit more if you
go up to an hour or something. Um but
yeah, ba basically they don't want to
keep this around because there this is a
huge amount of memory uh that they're
keeping in memory and so they want to
use it if it's working and and evict it
if it's not working. So um that that's
another policy that could change your
cash hit rate. The bad news for us as
users is the pricing doesn't change no
matter how good the provider is at
routing or um or cash eviction. So you
uh you might be paying just because they
evict you uh evict you too quickly which
seems a little bit unfair.
>> Um yeah
>> do they use like cash layering where you
can store it on device in memory that's
like adjusted to device and then on this
>> yeah so the that's a great question. So
the question was, do they use a cache
layering where you have like a fast
cache that's stored in the device and
then uh a slower cache that's stored on
disk or something like that? I actually
don't know the answer to that question.
That'd be a great uh like a great
follow-up for us to do. Um the open
source libraries also are probably not
as sophisticated as the closed libraries
because um if you look at all the people
on open router their job is to be really
good at serving and so you know they're
some of them might be using open source
libraries but they'll be building stuff
on top of them and that's kind of their
you know competitive differentiation. So
um like I I think
the internal solutions that inference
providers are likely to be you know a
bit better than the ones that are
available in open source too with
respect to that.
>> They usually offload to CPU from GPU.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. Because your GPU memory is so
precious. So yeah. Yeah.
>> Cool. Um so uh yeah. Oh, sorry. I
skipped a important part. So, what does
this mean? If you're just designing a
harness and you're not deploying models
or or anything like this, it means you
need to be super super careful to not
break your cache unintentionally.
So, remember that your cache only works
if the entire prefix is exactly the
same. And so there's a bunch of things
that we've thought about
uh doing but we decided are a very bad
idea because we don't want to break the
cache. So one thing that's completely
forbidden you should not do is don't
change the system message every time you
uh you take a step because that means
like no caching essentially. uh you
don't have a single message that you're
able to cache. So one thing one very
logical thing that you might think of is
okay I want to append the current time
and date to the system message uh so
that the agent knows what time it is. Do
not do this because the time and date
changes every step and so that will
break your cache. So if you do need to
append it, append it to the final user
message uh or the final uh tool call
result that you get. um and uh like
changing your um changing your tools uh
dynamically in the middle of the
conversation. You can do this. That's
okay. Um another thing is a very logical
thing that you might think of doing is
routing to a different model every time
you uh every time you take a step. So
it's like this step looks like a really
good model for you know a really power a
really good step for a really powerful
model. um like uh like I want to do this
step on Fable and then I want to do the
ne next three steps on um on a cheaper
model to save money. But the thing is
you're still paying
you're still paying the you know 10x
cost for Fable the next time you use uh
Fable. So you really need to be very uh
frugal in the amount of switching you're
going to be doing if you want to be
doing switching to save cost for
instance.
Cool. Um,
so the final thing I'd like to talk
about is context compaction. Um, how
many people know know about this? Use
this in your everyday coding agent use.
How many people are really excited when
it says compacting context?
[laughter]
That's nobody good. So um the the basic
idea behind context compaction is uh
that you have uh before
and uh this is you know all your
observations and actions that you might
have had. Um then after what you tend to
do is you tend to take your previous
context and you crush it down into just
the essence of the previous context. Um,
and so the reason why people are
like not excited about using this, uh,
perhaps obviously is if you do a bad job
at this, your agent forgets things. It
starts doing something completely
different and, uh, maybe deletes your
file system.
So
um we can view compaction as essentially
trying to come up with a previous
representation where your future action
sequence um you take your history, you
compact that, you get a working state
and you want your future action sequence
to be the same or you know similar or
possibly better um if uh after
compaction than it was before. Um
at the same time you also have a
constraint which your
state needs to be bounded. So it needs
to be small enough that you're happy to
continue work.
Um so if we look at what survives uh
compaction um there's different ways of
doing this. I'm going to cover the
different ways that people do this, but
a common strategy is to take some
anchors and these can be the very first
um like the very first things the user
said when they started the session for
instance. Um,
so, uh, one of the answers to the things
that I heard agents forget when I asked
the question, what do agents forget was
sometimes they forget the things at the
very beginning of the session? And
that actually might be a design bug in
the agent harness that you're using. Um,
because uh, some good agent harnesses
uh, like kind of intentionally avoid
deleting the stuff at the very beginning
of the session because they think it's
more important. Um, but it could also
be, you know, impossible to avoid
depending on the situation. Um, also you
want the stuff in the middle that's
encoded and put back into the context.
And then the recent tail is often kept
around. So often people will keep around
the the most recent actions.
Separately from this, I don't see this a
whole lot, but um, you can also add the
evidence to an evidence store. Actually,
no, sorry. I I'll correct this. Um, the
evidence is typically added to an
evidence store. Um, and at the very
least, if you're using a CLI coding
agent, usually your full history is
saved on disk somewhere. And so, if you
know where on disk, your coding agent
has saved all of this history. Even if
you lose stuff through compaction, you
can tell the coding agent to go back and
read the history, and it can, you know,
uh, read the history for you and find
the the previous results. Um but there
there are also uh possibly more
structured ways of doing this and so
then um you know other things can be
discarded.
Um so there's a few ways to decide uh
compaction policy. Um the first one is
the trigger and there's
um
essentially two ways of doing this. Um
one is a token threshold. So you limit
uh the token threshold. Uh so you can
say I'm I'm only going to use up to 200k
tokens. Once I go over 200k tokens, I'm
I'm going to compact the context.
Another thing is um like when you get
forced to do that by the provider. Um so
that's kind of like a hard limit on the
number of tokens you can have. Um
finally, you can also have a manual
request. And so uh a lot of uh kind of
coding agent toolkits for instance have
a slashcompact
uh like command that you can use to
compact the context.
Um then based on that uh you'll select
you might protect the beginning and keep
the recent tail and compact the older
region. Um replace it with a summary. Um
that summary can be a structured
summary. So sometimes uh they require a
tool call uh that says this and this and
this and this must be in the compaction
summary. Sometimes it's just free text.
Um there's also uh
I think this is only open AI uh
possibly. But basically they um they
compact into
something encrypted uh that you cannot
read. So you can't see how they're
compacting because they don't want you
to steal their uh their precious
compaction algorithm. Uh so uh so
there's that.
Um and then uh yeah, you can you can
keep on on working on that.
Um
so
one of the risks here is uh sometimes
you can compact over and over and over
again and the first time it works uh but
as you walk through more um you uh you
end up losing more and more. So again
this is one of the reasons why people
don't like compaction because it can
cause the agent to go off the rails.
Um so uh ba basically the way we
evaluate this is typically in a holistic
state. So you can vary the compaction
algorithm and evaluate it against
whatever benchmarks you're evaluating
against. I would like to warn you uh
about this. I have a a kind of like
story from when we were first developing
open hands which is um we actually I
think made one of the first like
production grade uh compaction
algorithms. We called it compression
then um and we evaluated it against
bbench which is a very common you know
benchmark for for coding agents and we
worked pretty hard on it like as a
research project for about a month or
something like that and we were like we
found this great compaction strategy. It
doesn't reduce our score at all. it's
saving us a lot of tokens. And then we
actually tried it in our um we tried it
in our our system and it made these
really silly mistakes like um sending a
pull request every time it compacted. So
it forgot that it had sent a pull
request to GitHub. And so uh you know we
would get five pull requests for the
same functionality because it had
forgotten. Um or you know it would
forget
user instructions that were sent in the
middle of the conversation because we
had only evaluated on single turn
conversations that had a single user
message and we were compacting away the
multiple user messages. So it's not just
good enough to benchmark uh unless you
have really really robust benchmarks
that represent every use case. You kind
of need to test them in the wild as
well.
Cool. Um so we're we're getting close to
time. Uh but yeah, basically uh what I
covered today is uh you know agent loops
grow very quickly. Uh we have a lot of
inference challenges in doing so. uh we
can handle uh efficiency problems
through architectures and um and caching
and uh compaction is kind of the way we
handle this uh once we expand beyond the
level that we can handle. So um that's
all I have. Uh if there is any questions
happy to happy to cover them and next
time we're going to be talking about
skills and memory. So this is like even
longer context over your entire uh your
entire time. Um, are there any questions
before we all uh all leave or
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, great question. Um, the question
was, do we consider sub agents as a way
to manage context? And yes, but we're
going to talk about sub aents later, so
I didn't cover them this time. Yeah.